♪The spring breeze blows through the world♪
♪ลมวสันต์พัดผ่านหมู่ชน♪
♪Blowing across the willow bank and the peach blossoms are brilliant♪
♪พัดกิ่งหลิวพลิ้วไหว ดอกท้อช่างดูสดใส♪
♪Who picks up the pen and writes that it's not too late to meet♪
♪ใครกันเล่าเขียนไว้ ไม่นานคงได้พบกัน♪
♪Looking back to see someone smiling happily♪
♪หันกลับไปมอง จึงเห็นรอยยิ้มงดงาม♪
♪Adding a touch of intensity to the depth of love♪
♪ในห้วงลึกของใจ ต่อเติมเส้นสายความรู้สึก♪
♪Being with you in the world of mortals♪
♪ในโลกกว้างใหญ่ มีเจ้าเป็นเพื่อนร่วมทาง♪
♪Whether it is a hustle or plain life♪
♪ไม่ว่าชีวิตจะสงบหรือวุ่นวาย♪
♪There will be no regrets in my life♪
♪ชาตินี้ไม่มีเสียดาย ไม่คิดขัดเคือง♪
♪See you in the next hundred years♪
♪สัญญาจะอยู่ด้วยกันจนวันสุดท้าย ไม่ลืมปัจจุบันที่เรายังเป็นหนุ่มสาว♪
♪I wish to stay and live up to the passing years♪
♪ไม่อยากปล่อยเวลาให้สูญเปล่า♪
♪Every morning and every night we are together♪
♪ทุกค่ำเช้าให้เรามีเรา♪
♪It turned out we've known each other since the beginning♪
♪ที่แท้ความรู้สึกใกล้ชิด เกิดขึ้นเพียงชั่วขณะจิต♪
♪He sent me a thousand words♪
♪เขาส่งจดหมายเนื้อความยาวเหยียด♪
♪She left a story♪
♪นางฝากเรื่องราวจารึกเอาไว้♪
♪The sound of guqin is like water and the shadow of the light is like a dream♪
♪เสียงพิณเสนาะโสต แสงโคมไฟราวอยู่ในฝัน♪
♪Everything is tactful♪
♪โลกใบนี้ช่างแสนงดงาม♪
♪Looking at the scenery and mountains with you♪
♪ได้อยู่ดูโลกกับเจ้า ใช้ชีวิตที่เหลือเคียงข้างกัน♪
♪Wait until the spring breeze blows♪
♪จนลมวสันต์พัดผ่านมาอีกครั้ง จึงรู้ว่ารักลึกซึ้งสุดหัวใจ♪
=A Female Student Arrives at the Imperial College=
=ศิษย์สาวป่วนสำนัก=
=Episode 19=
=ตอนที่ 19=
Qi.
อาฉี
I've wanted to marry you,
ข้าพูดมาตลอดว่าอยากแต่งกับเจ้า
but there is something important I haven't told you.
แต่มีคำพูดที่สำคัญที่สุดประโยคหนึ่ง ที่ไม่ได้บอกเจ้า
Zhuo Wen Yuan.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
Hear me out.
เจ้าฟังข้าพูดให้จบก่อน
I was exiled to the frontier fortress as a child.
ตอนเด็กข้าเร่ร่อนไปตามชายแดน
Only you treated me like your friend.
มีแค่เจ้าที่ปฏิบัติกับข้า อย่างเท่าเทียม
We wrote to each other after our parting.
หลังจากแยกย้าย เจ้ากับข้าก็ติดต่อกันทางจดหมาย
When I was all alone in Bianjing,
สำหรับข้าที่อยู่เปี้ยนจิงเพียงลำพัง
you were my only friend.
เจ้าเป็นเพื่อนเพียงคนเดียวของข้า
I made up my mind
ตอนนั้นที่ได้พบเจ้า
the moment I first met you.
ข้าก็ตัดสินใจแล้ว
I've always been in love with you.
จริง ๆ ข้าชอบเจ้ามาตลอด
Zhuo Wen Yuan...
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
I just realized
จู่ ๆ ข้าก็รู้สึกว่า
I'm not telling this for your sake,
คำพูดพวกนี้เหมือนไม่ได้จะบอกเจ้า
but for mine.
แต่เหมือนจะบอกกับตัวข้าเองต่างหาก
I know.
ข้ารู้
I know that clearly.
ข้าเห็นอยู่ว่า
You and Yan Yun Zhi
เจ้ากับเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
are in love with each other.
เจ้าสองคนรักกัน
However...
แต่ว่า
However, falling for you
เรื่องที่ข้ารักเจ้า
was my own choice.
ก็เป็นเรื่องของข้า
Even the best hunter
ต่อให้นายพรานเก่งกาจขนาดไหน
can't get any reward
ถ้าไม่มีเหยื่อให้ล่า
if there is no game around to hunt.
ถึงล่าไปก็ไม่ได้อะไร
We're adults now.
พวกเราก็โตกันแล้ว
This may be a great bow for me when I was little,
คันธนูนี้ต่อให้ดีขนาดไหน
but it doesn't do well for me now.
ก็ไม่เหมาะสมกับข้าแล้วตอนนี้
You can have it back.
คืนเจ้า
Zhuo Wen Yuan.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
I'll say this one last time.
ข้าขอบอกเจ้าอีกครั้ง
My heart only has a place for Yan Yun Zhi alone.
ในใจข้าซางฉีมีเพียงเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือคนเดียว
You should stop wasting your time on me.
เจ้าอย่าเสียเวลากับข้าอีกเลย
Only then
แบบนี้
can we still be friends.
เราถึงจะมีโอกาสเป็นเพื่อนกันต่อได้
See you around.
ไปเถอะ
If it weren't for our childhood,
ถ้าไม่ใช่เพราะความผูกพันในวัยเด็ก
things could have been different for us.
พวกเราคงไม่ได้มาถึงจุดนี้
Sang Qi.
ซางฉี
You left me with no other choice.
เจ้าเป็นคนบีบบังคับข้าเอง
You're back.
กลับมาแล้วเหรอ
Did you go out with Zhuo Wen Yuan?
ออกไปกับจั๋วเหวินหย่วนเหรอ
How do you know?
ท่านรู้ได้ไง
Should I not know?
ข้าไม่สมควรรู้เหรอไง
Don't take it wrongly.
ข้าไม่ได้หมายความอย่างนั้น
Since you were away for so long,
พวกเจ้าออกไปตั้งนาน
should I know what you talked about?
ข้าก็ควรรู้บ้างไหมว่าพวกเจ้าคุยอะไรกัน
Yes, you should know.
สมควร ข้าบอกเจ้าได้
As if I cared.
ข้าไม่อยากรู้หรอก
What's so funny about it?
เจ้ายังหัวเราะอีก หัวเราะอะไร
I'm serious.
ข้าจริงจังอยู่
Don't you want to know what we talked about?
ท่านไม่อยากรู้จริงเหรอว่าเราคุยอะไรกัน
Of course.
ก็ต้องอยากรู้สิ
But I shouldn't know.
แต่ก็ไม่ควรรู้
Who cares?
ยังจะมีอะไรควรไม่ควรอีก
It's the good manner.
เกิดเป็นคนต้องรู้จักวางตัว
I shouldn't know
ถึงข้าจะไม่ควรรู้
what you talked about,
ว่าพวกเจ้าคุยอะไรกัน
but I am concerned about it.
แต่ไม่ได้หมายความว่าข้าไม่ถือสา
That doesn't mean
อีกอย่างต่อให้บอกข้า
you needn't make it up to me.
ก็ยังต้องทำคุณไถ่โทษให้ข้าอยู่ดี
Are you still mad at me?
ยังโกรธอยู่เหรอ
Was that enough?
ถือว่าไถ่โทษแล้วหรือยัง
Come on.
ไม่แล้วมั้ง
I'm not mad at you.
ไม่โกรธแล้ว
When we get married,
ต่อไปเราแต่งงานกัน
where should we hold the wedding?
เจ้าอยากจัดพิธีที่ไหน
Married?
แต่งงานเหรอ
Isn't it a little too soon to discuss that?
พูดเรื่องนี้ตอนนี้เร็วไปไหม
But there should be a proposal before that, right?
ก่อนแต่งงานควรเข้าพิธีสู่ขอก่อนเหรอ
Yes.
จริงอยู่
That is the proper procedure.
ตามธรรมเนียมควรจะเริ่มจากพิธีสู่ขอ
But the proposal
แต่พิธีสู่ขอ
is usually handled by our parents.
ผู้ใหญ่ต้องจัดการ
They are in charge of the family visit.
แบบนี้พวกเราจะไม่มีส่วนร่วม
But the wedding is different.
ส่วนพิธีแต่งงานจะไม่ใช่แบบนี้
We can decide
กรณีพิธีแต่งงาน
what we want for the wedding.
เราทั้งคู่เป็นคนกำหนดเองได้
You only get this chance once.
เรื่องแบบนี้ชั่วชีวิตมีแค่ครั้งเดียว
I want it to be memorable for you.
ข้าอยากให้เจ้าประทับใจไปตลอดชีวิต
Let's have it in the Imperial College.
จัดที่สำนักศึกษาเป็นไง
We met and fell in love here.
เรารู้จักกันที่สำนักศึกษา
I'm sure it'd be meaningful for Yu as well.
อีกอย่างสถานที่นี้สำคัญกับพี่อวี่มาก
Fair enough. We'll have it in the Imperial College.
ได้ ที่สำนักศึกษา
However,
แต่ว่า
I want to hold a banquet with my maiden family at the frontier fortress.
ข้าอยากกลับไปจัดพิธีอีกรอบที่ชายแดนด้วย
Sure. As you wish.
ได้ ตามใจเจ้า
Well,
ถ้างั้น
what about the names of our kids?
ในอนาคตลูกของเราชื่ออะไรดี
Tell me.
เจ้าว่ามา
How should we name them?
ชื่ออะไรดี
This is too sudden.
จู่ ๆ พูดเรื่องนี้ทำไม
♪The quiet streets in spring♪
♪วสันตฤดูหนทางเงียบสงัด ทิวไม้ไหวตามแรงลมโบกพัด♪
♪Standing at the edge of the city at sunset♪
♪ริมกำแพงเมืองยามอาทิตย์อัสดง♪
♪Your dress fluttering in the wind♪
♪ความงามของเจ้า ดึงดูดใจให้ข้ามาเชยชม♪
♪The clouds are curling over the wind♪
♪เมฆาลอยเลื่อนตามแรงลม ฝนโปรยปรายใบไม้ร่วงหล่น♪
♪If the sky grows old someday♪
♪ราวกับโลกใบนี้โรยราลง♪
♪You and I will surely♪
♪ข้ากับเจ้าจักต้อง สานต่อบทเพลงแห่งรัก♪
♪Together in the world of mortals♪
♪ตราบจนชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
Brother,
ท่านพี่
I have great news for you.
ข้ามีเรื่องสำคัญมากจะบอกกับพี่
He...
เขา
He actually said he wanted to marry me.
เขา จู่ ๆ พูดออกมาว่าจะขอข้าแต่งงาน
I didn't expect he would
ข้าเองก็นึกไม่ถึงว่า
be so thoughtful and attentive.
เขาวางแผนอย่างละเอียดรอบคอบ
He knows the Imperial College holds a special place in my heart.
เขารู้ว่าสำนักศึกษามีความหมาย กับข้าขนาดไหน
He proposed we should hold our wedding
ไม่นึกว่าเขาจะเสนอเองว่า
at the Imperial College.
ให้จัดพิธีแต่งที่สำนักศึกษา
I told him
พอข้าบอกไปว่า
I'd like to have a banquet with my maiden family at the frontier fortress.
ข้าอยากกลับไปชายแดนจัดพิธีซ้ำอีกรอบ
He agreed without any hesitation.
เขาตอบตกลงโดยไม่ลังเลเลย
He even told me
เขาพูดอีกว่า
one of our kids could take my surname.
ลูกสองคน คนหนึ่งใช้แซ่ข้าได้
The other kid can take his surname.
อีกคนค่อยใช้แซ่เขา
In that case,
แบบนี้
we will have two kids...
เราก็จะมีลูกกันสองคน
No, he said there would be more than two kids.
ไม่สิ เขาบอกว่าไม่ใช่แค่ลูกสองคน
We could have a bunch of children.
อยากมีลูกหลาย ๆ คน
I feel so shy.
น่าอายชะมัด
Two children...
ลูกสองคน
If we have four children,
ถ้ามีลูกกันสี่คน
two will take his surname,
สองคนใช้แซ่เขา
the other two will take mine.
อีกสองคนใช้แซ่ข้า
(The daughter of Sang family has grown up.)
(ลูกสาวบ้านซางโตเป็นสาว)
(So, the day has finally come for me.)
(ในที่สุดข้าซางเวยคงต้อง ยอมรับความจริงข้อนี้)
Yu.
พี่อวี่
(Cenotaph of the beloved son, Sang Yu) I have great news for you.
(สุสานซางอวี่ผู้เป็นลูกที่รักยิ่ง) ข้ามีข่าวดีจะบอกกับเจ้า
Qi lived up to your expectation.
อาฉีไม่ทำให้เจ้าผิดหวัง
She is ranked 18th place of the Second Class Degree.
รอบนี้สอบจอหงวน สอบได้ตำแหน่งเอ้อร์เจี่ยอันดับสิบแปด
As promised,
เราตกลงกันไว้ว่า
we'll announce our relationship
รอบนี้สอบจอหงวนเสร็จ
after the imperial examination.
เราจะประกาศให้ทุกคนรู้เรื่องของเราสองคน
Not only that,
ไม่ใช่แค่นั้น
I stayed up all night to prepare the bridewealth.
เมื่อคืนข้าได้เตรียมสินสอดไว้พร้อมแล้ว
I'll propose to her today at your residence.
วันนี้จะไปจวนเจ้าเพื่อสู่ขอน้องสาวเจ้า
Yu, I won't let you down.
พี่อวี่ ข้าจะไม่ทำให้เจ้าผิดหวัง
I'll do whatever I can
ข้าจะดูแลอาฉี
to take great care of Qi.
ให้ดีที่สุด
Impressive.
เจ้าตัวดี
It seems your destiny is intertwined with our Sang family.
เจ้ามีวาสนากับคนสกุลซางจริงนะ
Grand Commandant Sang.
คำนับซางไท่เว่ย
I've heard you were close with Yu.
ได้ข่าวมานานแล้วว่าเจ้ากับลูกอวี่ มีความสัมพันธ์ที่ดีเยี่ยม
You never stop visiting his grave even after so many years.
ผ่านไปหลายปีเจ้ายังอุตส่าห์มาเยี่ยมตลอด
It was my greatest honor
ชีวิตนี้ได้เป็นเพื่อนสนิทกับพี่อวี่
to be his friend.
ถือเป็นโชคอันสูงสุดของข้า
But Yu and Qi are not the same.
ลูกอวี่ก็ส่วนลูกอวี่ อาฉีก็ส่วนอาฉี
I'll get straight to the point.
ข้าจะไม่พูดอ้อมค้อมนะ
I'm against your marriage with Qi.
เรื่องเจ้ากับอาฉี ข้าไม่อนุญาต
Does something concern you, Grand Commandant Sang?
ซางไท่เว่ยมีเรื่องกังวลใจอะไรไม่ทราบ
Whatever you demand,
ไม่ว่าอย่างไร
I'll do my best to meet the requirement.
ข้าจะต้องทำให้ท่านพอใจถึงที่สุด
I'll be frank.
ข้าเป็นคนตรงไปตรงมา
I had hoped for someone else to marry her.
ในใจข้า เจ้าไม่ใช่ตัวเลือก ที่เหมาะสมที่สุด
I'm grateful that you helped my daughter finish the imperial examination.
ข้าขอขอบคุณที่ช่วยให้ลูกข้าสอบจอหงวนได้
But she is my only daughter.
ข้าเองก็มีลูกสาวคนเดียว
I won't let her feel aggrieved.
ข้าไม่ยอมให้ลูกต้อง ต้องเจ็บช้ำแม้เพียงสักเล็กน้อย
I must find her
ข้าต้องการ
a husband who can keep her safe.
คนที่ปกป้องให้ลูกข้าแต่งกับ ตระกูลที่ปกป้องลูกข้าได้
Grand Commandant Sang.
ซางไท่เว่ย
I understand your concern.
ข้าเข้าใจความหมายของท่าน
But I will propose nonetheless.
แต่ยังไงข้าก็จะไปสู่ขอลูกสาวท่านอยู่ดี
I'll keep trying until you agree.
รอบนี้ท่านไม่อนุญาต ข้าก็จะมาใหม่
I will prove my resolve.
ข้าอยากให้ทุกคนเห็นความมุ่งมั่นของข้า
Suit yourself.
อยากทรมานตัวเองก็เชิญตามสบาย
Let's see how long you can keep it up.
อยากรู้ว่าเจ้าจะทนได้ถึงเมื่อไร
Leave.
เจ้าไปเถอะ
Yu, I'll leave for now.
พี่อวี่ ข้าไปก่อน
(Grand Preceptor's Residence)
(จวนไท่ซือ)
You are back.
กลับมาแล้วเหรอ
Greetings, Mother.
ลูกขอคารวะท่านแม่
I have an announcement for you.
มีอยู่เรื่องหนึ่งที่ข้าอยากบอกท่านแม่
Did you get into
คงไม่ใช่ไปก่อเรื่อง
some sort of trouble again?
ให้ข้าต้องปวดหัวอีกแล้วสินะ
I only came to tell you that
ในที่สุดลูกก็เรียนจบแล้ว
because I've graduated.
ถึงได้กล้ามาบอกกับท่านแม่
I'm in love with someone.
ข้ามีคนที่ข้าชอบแล้ว
I hope to get your blessing.
จะขอให้แม่
Allow me to propose to her.
ไปช่วยข้าสู่ขอที่จวนด้วย
Sure.
ดีสิ
I've been worried
ข้ากังวลใจแทบขาด
about your marriage.
เพราะเรื่องนี้
The bridewealth is ready.
สินสอดข้าก็เตรียมไว้นานมากแล้ว
Whose daughter is it?
เป็นลูกสาวสกุลไหนเหรอ
The Sang family.
สกุลซาง
Grand Commandant Sang?
ซางไท่เว่ย
I heard the rumors.
ข้าเคยได้ยินมาเหมือนกัน
But I'm surprised you want to marry her.
แต่ไม่คิดว่าเจ้าจะแต่งกับนาง
You already know?
ท่านแม่ก็รู้เรื่องแล้วเหรอ
I was worried...
ตอนแรกข้ายังห่วงอยู่เลย
I know what worries you.
ข้ารู้ว่าเจ้ากังวลอะไร
Those from the Sang family
คนจากสกุลซางแต่ละคน
are usually very expressive.
ดูโลดโผนไปนิด
That's why people gossip about them.
คนทั่วไปเอาแต่ซุบซิบนินทากัน
Were you worried I might disagree
เจ้าคงห่วงว่าข้าไม่อนุญาต
with your plan?
งานแต่งครั้งนี้สินะ
I don't care about the gossips.
ข้าไม่สนหรอกว่าข้างนอกเขาจะว่ายังไง
I've been in love with her for so long.
ข้าชอบนางมานานแล้ว
She is energetic and cheerful, thoughtful and gentle.
นางผู้นี้ร่าเริงแจ่มใส ละเอียดเอาใจใส่
She forms her own opinions,
และเป็นคนมีความคิดเป็นของตัวเอง
unlike average young ladies.
ไม่เหมือนหญิงทั่วไปที่ไหน
I understand.
ข้ารู้แล้ว
She sounds like a nice person.
ดูเจ้าพูดเสียดิบดีขนาดนี้
I was told she grew up at the frontier.
ได้ข่าวว่านางไปเติบโตที่ชายแดน
So, she must be strong.
ร่างกายกำยำแข็งแรง
Our Yan family will have plenty of grandchildren.
สกุลเหยียนของเรา จะได้มีผู้สืบทอดที่มั่นคง
But she does take great care
นางเองก็ดูแลสกุลซาง
of her family.
เป็นอย่างดีในทุกเรื่อง
Her cooking is outstanding too.
ทำอาหารก็อร่อย
A virtuous lady indeed.
แล้วยังนิสัยดีมากอีกด้วย
I can see why Grand Commandant Sang is so fond of her.
มิน่าล่ะ ซางไท่เว่ยที่ได้หวงแหนขนาดนี้
He treats her well.
ไท่เว่ยก็ห่วงใยดูแลนางเป็นพิเศษ
She must be at the right age for marriage now.
นางน่าจะอยู่ในวัยออกเรือนแล้วสินะ
But since Grand Commandant Sang is so fond of her,
แต่คนที่ซางไท่เว่ยหวงแหนขนาดนี้
what are your chances?
เจ้ามั่นใจได้แค่ไหน
I haven't talked to Grand Commandant Sang formally
ลูกไม่เคยพูดคุยเรื่องนี้
about this matter.
กับซางไท่เว่ยอย่างเป็นทางการ
It's all right.
ไม่เป็นไร
With my help,
ให้แม่ออกหน้าแทนเจ้า
everything will work out just fine.
ไม่มีคู่รักคู่ไหนที่ไม่ลงเอยกัน
Let's not wait any longer.
ชักช้าไม่ได้ ใครขอก่อนได้ก่อน
Today is a good day.
วันนี้ฤกษ์งามยามดี
We must go there right now.
อย่างนั้นเราไปกันตอนนี้เลย
Mother, take the bridewealth with you.
ถ้างั้น ถ้างั้นท่านแม่ไปเตรียมสินสอดไว้
It's an important day,
วันสำคัญขนาดนี้
I need someone important with me.
ลูกต้องไปพาคนสำคัญมาคนหนึ่งก่อน
Try to calm down a little!
ดูสิเจ้า ลนลานยิ่งกว่าลิงอีก
Check the inventory,
ไปตรวจสอบให้ครบ
make sure we have everything.
อย่าให้ขาดแม้แต่อย่างเดียว
Yes, Madam.
เจ้าค่ะ ฮูหยิน
Lian Pian.
เหลียนเพียน
Where is she?
อยู่ไหน
Master, what's the matter?
ใต้เท้า เกิดอะไรขึ้นเหรอคะ
It's a serious matter,
เกิดเรื่องใหญ่ขนาดนี้
so why didn't you inform me?
ทำไมเจ้าไม่เคยเล่าให้ข้าฟังแม้แต่นิด
Young Master Yan and I are not in love.
ข้า ข้ากับคุณชายสกุลเหยียน ไม่มีอะไรต่อกัน
We didn't do anything inappropriate.
ไม่เคยทำเรื่องที่เกินเลยเจ้าค่ะ
You?
เจ้า
You and Yan Xiao Lang?
เจ้ากับเหยียนเสี่ยวหลาง
How silly of me.
ข้าเองยังสับสนเลย
I forgot you were about the same age as Qi.
ลืมเลยว่าเจ้าอายุพอ ๆ กับอาฉี
It's time you get married as well.
สมควรจะออกเรือนได้แล้ว
You've served the Sang family for years.
หลายปีมานี้เจ้าอยู่จวนสกุลซาง
I never paid you too much attention.
ปกติข้าก็ไม่เคยใส่ใจเจ้าเป็นพิเศษ
I didn't notice
นึกไม่ถึงว่า
you had special feelings for Yan Xiao Lang.
เจ้ากับเหยียนซานหลางมีใจให้กัน
I'm just a servant.
ข้าเป็นแค่สาวใช้คนหนึ่ง
The Yan family is beyond my league.
ไม่อาจเอื้อมจะแต่งเข้าสกุลเหยียน
If he can decide for his own marriage,
ถ้าเขาตัดสินใจเรื่องงานแต่งเองได้
I don't mind at all.
ข้าก็ยินดีเป็นพ่อบุญธรรม
You can marry him as my goddaughter.
ให้เจ้าได้แต่งออกไปอยู่สกุลเหยียน
If the Yan family doesn't buy it,
ถ้าสกุลเหยียนยังคาใจเรื่องนี้
it's not like
สกุลซางของเราเอง
the Sang family is too concerned with rites and traditions.
ก็ไม่ติดปัญหาอะไร
I can include your name in our genealogy book.
ให้เจ้าเข้าเป็นคนในสกุลเราก็ได้
Father.
ท่านพ่อ
You're the best father in the whole Bianjing!
ท่านเป็นพ่อที่ดีที่สุด ในเมืองเปี้ยนจิงแล้ว
No! You're the best father in the entire world!
ไม่สิ ท่านเป็นพ่อที่ดีที่สุดในโลกเลย
Lian Pian, I'm your sister now.
เหลียนเพียน ไหนเจ้า ลองเรียกข้าว่าพี่สาวสิ
Sis... Young Lady!
พี่... คุณหนู
You...
นี่เจ้า
Sister.
พี่
Come.
มานี่
What's wrong?
เกิดอะไรขึ้นเหรอคะ
I'm fine.
ข้าไม่มีอะไร
Po.
อาพัว
Close all the gates.
รีบไปปิดประตูทั้งหมดในจวนให้มิดชิด
Make sure no one comes in.
ไม่ว่าใครก็ห้ามเข้ามา
Father, why are we closing all the gates?
ท่านพ่อ ทำไมต้องปิดประตูในจวนให้มิดชิด
Lian Pian.
เหลียนเพียน
Don't you find my father odd?
เจ้ารู้สึกไหมว่าช่วงนี้ท่านพ่อดูแปลกไป
His mood is unpredictable.
เดี๋ยวก็ดีใจ เดี๋ยวก็โมโห
Not at all.
ไม่นะคะ
I think he is nice.
ข้ารู้สึกว่าใต้เท้าปกติดี
Say "Sister."
เรียกข้าพี่สาวสักคำสิ
Sister.
พี่สาว
My younger sister.
น้องสาว
Come now, follow me to the Grand Commandant's Residence.
ไป รีบตามข้าไปจวนไท่เว่ยเดี๋ยวนี้
The Grand Commandant's Residence?
จวนไท่เว่ยเหรอ
For what?
ธุระอะไร
I must propose to Lian Pian today.
วันนี้ข้าจะไปสู่ขอเหลียนเพียน
Hold on.
เดี๋ยวนะ
It'll be double the delight
เห็นท่าวันนี้จะมีข่าวดีสองเรื่อง
and joy.
งานมงคลคู่
See?
เจ้าดูนี่
(Secretariat Chancellery)
(จวนจงซู)
Let's go, get on the carriage.
ไปกัน ขึ้นรถเถอะ
You...
เจ้า
(Grand Commandant's Residence)
(จวนไท่เว่ย)
Sorry.
ต้องขออภัย
We do not accept any visits today.
วันนี้จวนไท่เว่ยไม่รับแขก
Please come some other day.
วันหน้าเชิญมาใหม่ค่ะ
You must let me in.
ไม่รับแขกไม่ได้แล้ว
It concerns
ไม่งั้นก็จะพลาด
the future of the Sang family.
งานมงคลของสกุลซางแล้ว
We from the Yan family don't enjoy being kept at the doorstep.
สกุลเหยียนของข้ายิ่งไม่ชอบ ถูกปฏิเสธด้วย
Madam Yan.
เหยียนฮูหยิน
I apologize.
ข้าน้อยเสียมารยาทแล้ว
Please come in.
เชิญท่านเข้ามาเลยค่ะ
I'll inform my Master.
ข้าไปแจ้งให้ใต้เท้าทราบก่อน
Madam, please.
เชิญฮูหยินค่ะ
The girl has keen eyes.
สาวใช้คนนี้ ฉลาดหลักแหลมเหมือนกันนะ
Madam Yan.
เหยียนฮูหยิน
I didn't expect you to visit so soon.
นึกไม่ถึงว่าจะมาเร็วขนาดนี้
Grand Commandant Sang.
ซางไท่เว่ย
I guess you know why I'm here.
ท่านคงรู้แล้วสินะว่าข้ามาด้วยเรื่องอันใด
Since it's about marriage,
ไหน ๆ ก็เป็นเรื่องมงคล
let's get down to business.
เราไปเข้าประเด็นกันเลยแล้วกัน
If you're willing to accept it,
ถ้าฮูหยินไม่ติดขัดอะไร
I'll be glad for sure.
ข้าก็ยินดีอย่างยิ่ง
This is the children's decision.
ข้าก็แค่ตามใจพวกเด็ก ๆ
I'm here for the sake of rite.
พวกเราก็แค่สู่ขอกันพอเป็นพิธี
Welcome.
เชิญ
Yan Yan mentioned it yesterday,
เมื่อวานเหยียนเหยี่ยนเพิ่งพูดถึง
and now he brought so many gifts for the proposal.
วันนี้ก็ขนของตั้งมากมายมาสู่ขอเจ้า
Yan Yan must have got his strong-willed personality
เหยียนเหยี่ยนนี่รวดเร็วทันใจ
from his parents.
เหมือนกันทั้งตระกูลจริง ๆ
Both he and his mother are quick to take action.
แม่ลูกคู่นี้ทำอะไรรวดเร็วทันใจ
I underestimated him.
ข้ามองเขาผิดไปจริง ๆ
Let's go.
ไป
I didn't get a close look.
ก่อนหน้าไม่ได้ตั้งใจดู
But now I can see how lovely she is.
มาวันนี้ได้เห็นหน้าดูน่ารักเหมือนกันนะ
Lovely.
น่ารัก
- Grand Commandant. - Grand Commandant Sang.
- ไท่เว่ย - ซางไท่เว่ย
- Mother. - Madam Yan.
- ท่านแม่ - เหยียนฮูหยิน
Mother, you made my wish come true.
ได้ท่านแม่ช่วย คราวนี้ลูกได้สมหวังแล้ว
All right, everyone is here.
ก็ดี มากันครบแล้ว
Let's not waste any more time.
ถ้างั้นข้าเข้าประเด็นเลยแล้วกัน
Grand Commandant Sang.
ซางไท่เว่ย
(Letter of Eight Characters)
(สูติบัตร)
Sang Qi.
ซางฉี
You will soon be my daughter-in-law.
วันหน้าเจ้าก็จะเป็นสะใภ้สกุลเหยียนแล้วนะ
What?
อะไรนะ
- No! - You got it all wrong.
ไม่ค่ะ ไม่ค่ะ ไม่ค่ะ
Madam Yan.
เหยียน... เหยียนฮูหยิน
You misunderstood.
ท่าน ท่านเข้าใจผิดแล้ว
Yan Yan isn't marrying me.
เหยียนเหยี่ยนไม่ได้จะสู่ขอข้า
I'm not marrying Yan Yan either.
คนที่ข้าจะแต่งงานด้วยไม่ใช่เหยียนเหยี่ยน
Look at you.
มาดูหน่อย มาดูหน่อย
Calm down, don't be so nervous.
เป็นเด็กดีนะ ไม่ต้องตื่นเต้น
Your tongue is twisted.
ดูเจ้าสิพูดผิดพูดถูก
I'm serious.
ข้าไม่ได้พูดอะไรผิด
Madam Yan.
เหยียนฮูหยิน
Sang Qi is marrying me.
คนที่ซางฉีจะแต่งงานด้วยคือข้า
Is this a misunderstanding?
ฮูหยินคงเข้าใจอะไรบางอย่างผิด
Yes.
ใช่
Why didn't you tell me beforehand?
แล้วทำไมท่านไม่บอกก่อน
I told you yesterday.
ข้าบอกแล้วไง
I'm a man of my word.
ข้าพูดจริงทำจริง
I'm serious about marrying you.
เรื่องแต่งไม่ใช่เรื่องล้อเล่น
Madam, for your information,
เหยียนฮูหยินอาจยังไม่รู้ว่า
people already know
เรื่องระหว่างข้ากับซางฉี
about my relationship with Sang Qi.
ทุกคนต่างก็รู้ดี
I'm visiting
ที่ข้ามาวันนี้
to inform Grand Commandant Sang of our relationship.
ก็เพื่อเรียนให้ซางไท่เว่ยทราบ เรื่องของเราสองคน
Then, I'll propose to Sang Qi formally.
แล้วข้าค่อยมาสู่ขอซางฉีอีกครั้ง
Grand Commandant Sang, this is the letter containing my Eight Characters.
ซางไท่เว่ย นี่เป็นสูติบัตรของข้า
Not now.
รออีกหน่อย
Deputy Chief Yan, first comes, first served.
เยี่ยนซือเย่ ใครมาก่อนได้ก่อน
A proposal is no child's play.
อีกอย่าง เรื่องสู่ขอเป็นเรื่องใหญ่
Your parents must be present for the matter.
ต้องให้พ่อแม่ของทั้งสองฝ่าย เป็นคนตัดสินใจ
Why are you here all by yourself?
ทำไมวันนี้เจ้าถึงมาตามลำพัง
Do not try to take away the Yan family's bride.
อย่ามาแย่งคนไปจากสกุลเหยียนเราเลยนะ
Madam Yan.
เหยียนฮูหยิน
It's best that you ask Yan Yan who he's here to
ขอให้ฮูหยินลองถามเหยียนเหยี่ยนเสียก่อน
propose to.
ที่มาวันนี้จะสู่ขอใคร
Yes.
ใช่ ใช่ ใช่
The Sang family only has one daughter.
สกุลซางมีแค่ลูกสาวคนเดียว
Do you expect my son to marry the servant?
หรือจะให้ลูกชายข้าแต่งกับสาวใช้บ้านนี้
Yan?
ลูกเหยี่ยน
Outrageous!
เหลวไหล
Your father is the Grand Perceptor!
พ่อของเจ้าเป็นถึงไท่ซือ
How can you marry a servant?
เจ้ากลับจะแต่งกับสาวใช้
Madam Yan.
เหยียนฮูหยิน
That was a little inappropriate.
คำพูดของท่านอาจจะไม่ค่อยเหมาะเท่าไร
Lian Pian and I grew up together.
ข้ากับเหลียนเพียนโตด้วยกันมา
I treat her as my equal.
ไม่เคยแบ่งแยกว่า ใครเป็นคุณหนูใครเป็นสาวใช้
We do chores together
พวกเราลำบากด้วยกันมา
and eat at the same table.
กินข้าวก็กินร่วมโต๊ะกัน
Right, Father?
ใช่ไหม ท่านพ่อ
Our family has never looked down on Lian Pian.
สกุลเราไม่เคยดูถูกดูแคลนเหลียนเพียน
Madam Yan.
เหยียนฮูหยิน
I couldn't introduce her to you because of the sudden visit.
ฮูหยินมาแบบไม่ทันตั้งตัว ข้าเลยยังไม่ได้แนะนำ
I basically raise Lian Pian myself.
เหลียนเพียนอยู่กับข้ามาแต่เด็กจนโต
I see her as my daughter.
ข้ามองนางเป็นเหมือนลูกสาวมาตลอด
Yes!
ใช่
I'm planning to include her name
ข้าเองยังตั้งใจว่าจะหาวันฤกษ์งามยามดี
in our genealogy book.
ใส่ชื่อนางลงในทำเนียบวงศ์ตระกูล
That will officially make her the Third Young Lady of the Sang family.
เป็นลูกคนที่สามของสกุลซางข้า
Grand Commandant Sang, we are both reputable families.
ซางไท่เว่ย พวกเราล้วนเป็นคนมีฐานะ
How could you agree to this nonsense?
ท่านจะทำเรื่องผิดต่อขนบธรรมเนียม แบบนี้ได้อย่างไร
A servant
สาวใช้คนหนึ่ง
can never marry into my family!
จะให้แต่งเข้ามาในตระกูลเป็นไปได้ไง
Even as a concubine
ต่อให้แต่งในฐานะอนุ
or a nameless mistress,
หรือแม้แต่เมียเก็บที่ไม่มีฐานะใด ๆ
I still won't allow it!
ก็เป็นไปไม่ได้
Sang Qi is the only one
ในจวนของท่าน
who deserves to be married to the Yan family!
มีเพียงซางฉีเท่านั้นที่มีคุณสมบัติ พอที่จะแต่งเข้าสกุลเหยียน
Mother, I'm not marrying Sang Qi.
ท่านแม่ ข้าไม่ต้องการแต่งกับซางฉี
I must marry Lian Pian!
ข้าจะแต่งกับเหลียนเพียน
Silence!
หุบปาก
Madam Yan, calm down.
เหยียนฮูหยินอย่าเพิ่งโกรธเคือง
I'm afraid today
เรื่องสู่ขอในวันนี้
is not the best time for a proposal.
เห็นทีจะไม่สำเร็จ
Lian Pian, don't worry.
เหลียนเพียน เจ้าก็ไม่ต้องรีบร้อน
Deputy Chief Yan.
เยี่ยนซือเย่
You should come at another time.
ส่วนเจ้า เอาไว้วันหน้าค่อยมาใหม่แล้วกัน
Madam Yan,
เหยียนฮูหยิน
you should discuss it with your son.
เชิญกลับไปพูดคุยกับเหยียนเสี่ยวหลาง ให้ดีก่อน
I may be a martial artist,
ข้าซางเวยถึงจะเป็นคนฝึกยุทธ
but when it comes to my children's marriage,
แต่การแต่งงานเป็นเรื่องสำคัญของลูก ๆ
I won't make any reckless decisions.
ข้าต้องคิดอย่างรอบคอบค่อยตัดสินใจ
Well said, Grand Commandant Sang.
ที่ซางไท่เว่ยว่ามาจริงแท้แน่นอน
We shall leave now.
ถ้างั้นพวกเราขออำลา
Yan Yan!
เหยียนเหยี่ยน
(Grand Commandant's Residence)
(จวนไท่เว่ย)
I'm happy that you came to propose.
เรื่องที่เจ้ามาสู่ขอทำให้ข้าดีใจมาก
But I didn't know
แต่นึกไม่ถึงว่า
it'd turn out this way.
เรื่องราวจะกลายเป็นแบบนี้
A lot has happened today.
เรื่องที่เกิดขึ้นในแต่ละวัน
My mood is all ruined.
ทำให้ใจข้าว้าวุ่นไปหมด
Whether Yan Yan deserves to marry Lian Pian
เหยียนเหยี่ยนจะคู่ควร กับเหลียนเพียนหรือไม่
depends on what he does after this.
ขึ้นอยู่กับการกระทำ ของเหยียนเหยี่ยนต่อจากนี้แล้ว
I couldn't propose because
เรื่องมาถึงจุดนี้เพราะเหยียนฮูหยิน
of Madam Yan's tantrum,
พิธีสู่ขอเลยไม่สำเร็จ
are you disappointed?
เจ้าจะผิดหวัง
Are you getting restless?
และว้าวุ่นไหม
Me?
ข้าเหรอ
Not at all.
ข้าไม่ว้าวุ่นเหรอ
You brought your letter of Eight Characters
ท่านถึงกับเอาสูติบัตรมา
to my residence,
สู่ขอข้าแล้ว
you're not going anywhere.
จะหนีไปไหนได้อีก
Indeed.
จริงด้วย
You father said
พ่อเจ้าก็บอกเองว่า
I should come at another time.
ให้ข้ามาวันหลัง
I'll come again very soon.
ข้าไม่ทำให้เจ้ารอนานแน่
Father.
ท่านพ่อ
Grand Commandant Sang.
ซางไท่เว่ย
When did you come here?
ท่านมาตั้งแต่เมื่อไร
I think I should come here more often.
สงสัยข้าคงต้องมาที่นี่บ่อย ๆ แล้วมั้ง
Grand Commandant Sang, I shall go now.
ซางไท่เว่ย ข้าน้อยอำลาก่อน
(Grand Commandant's Residence) Stay safe.
กลับดี ๆ นะ
Father.
ท่านพ่อ
Do you have something to tell me?
ท่านมีเรื่องจะคุยกับข้าใช่ไหม
What was that all about?
นี่มันเกิดเรื่องอะไรขึ้น
Both men who came today
วันนี้มาทีสองคน
were disappointing.
ใช้ไม่ได้ทั้งคู่
I know.
ข้ารู้
You think Madam Yan is too strong-willed
พ่อคงคิดว่าเหยียนฮูหยินตรงไปตรงมาเกินไป
and worried Lian Pian might get bullied after marrying Yan Yan.
เหลียนเพียนแต่งไปบ้านนั้นคงถูกรังแก
I understand your concern.
เรื่องนี้ข้าเข้าใจอยู่
But what about the Deputy Chief?
แต่เรื่องข้ากับซือเย่ทำไมพ่อไม่อนุญาต
First of all, they both came to propose.
ข้อแรก แต่ละคนมาสู่ขอแบบลุกลี้ลุกลน
He handed me the letter as soon as they arrived.
เข้าจวนปุ๊บก็ยัดสูติบัตรใส่มือข้า
Does he have no respect for me at all?
ยังเห็นข้าเป็นหัวหน้าครอบครัวอยู่ไหม
Secondly, Yan Yun Zhi is the son of Chancellor Yan's concubine.
ข้อสอง เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือเป็นลูกของเมียรอง
Chancellor Yan never cares too much
เสนาบดีเยี่ยนเย็นชาได้
about his own son,
แม้แต่กับลูกชายคนนี้
it'll be worse for you.
กับเจ้ายิ่งไม่ต้องพูดถึง
He came without even informing his father.
เขาไม่ให้สุ้มให้เสียงจู่ ๆ ก็มาสู่ขอเจ้า
Thirdly, he has a weird personality. He does things his own way.
ข้อสาม นิสัยเขาแปลกประหลาด ทำตามใจ
He's obnoxious.
เป็นคนดื้อรั้น
He's obnoxious?
เขาเนี่ยนะดื้อรั้น
Father, don't forget,
พ่ออย่าลืมนะ
you're an obnoxious old man.
พ่อก็เป็นคนดื้อรั้น
I'm an obnoxious young lady.
ข้าเองก็เป็นคนดื้อรั้น
We both have weird personalities.
เราสองคนนิสัยแปลกประหลาด
So why do you look down on him?
แล้วพ่อรังเกียจเขาทำไม
In that regard,
ตรงจุดนี้ จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
Zhuo Wen Yuan can do much better than him.
เป็นคนเพียบพร้อมกว่าเขาเยอะ
Why do you bring him up?
พ่อพูดถึงเขาทำไม
Can you not poke at my sore spot?
พ่ออย่าเอาแต่ค่อนแคะคนอื่นได้ไหม
This has nothing to do with him.
เรื่องนี้เกี่ยวอะไรกับเขาด้วย
You...
นี่เจ้า
Father!
ท่านพ่อ
Lian Pian.
เหลียนเพียน
Don't get upset
เรื่องที่เหยียนฮูหยินพูดเมื่อครู่
over what Madam Yan said just now.
เจ้าอย่าไปจำใส่ใจนะ
Don't worry, Young Lady.
คุณหนูไม่ต้องกังวล
I was ready for it anyway.
ข้าเองเตรียมใจไว้แล้ว
It was a lot better than I had imagined.
สถานการณ์ดูไม่หนักหน่วง เหมือนที่คิดไว้แต่แรกด้วยซ้ำ
Madam Yan's reaction
ที่เหยียนฮูหยินทำไปวันนี้
had me frightened as well.
ข้าเองก็แอบตกใจเหมือนกัน
But don't worry, Lian Pian.
แต่เจ้าไม่ต้องห่วงนะเหลียนเพียน
Both my father and I support you.
ข้ากับท่านพ่อสนับสนุนเจ้าเต็มที่
We're making you part of the family.
จะให้เจ้าเป็นน้องสาวข้า
Your name will be in our genealogy book.
ให้เจ้าเข้ามาอยู่ในทำเนียบสกุลซางของเรา
It's not to please the Yan family.
ไม่ใช่เพื่อรับมือกับสกุลเหยียน
We do so because I already
แต่เป็นเพราะข้ามองเจ้า
see you as my sister.
เป็นเหมือนน้องสาวคนหนึ่งแต่แรกแล้ว
I appreciate the thought.
ข้าเข้าใจความหมายคุณหนู
But
แค่ว่าจู่ ๆ จะให้ข้า
I feel conflicted to call you my sister
หยุดเรียกท่านว่าคุณหนู
after so long.
ข้ายังรู้สึกอึดอัด
You should help Deputy Chief Yan too.
อีกอย่าง คุณหนูต้องช่วยเยี่ยนซือเย่ คิดแผนด้วย
Judging by Master's temper,
นิสัยใต้เท้าก็รู้อยู่
he won't be easy to please.
ท่านเป็นคนโน้มน้าวยาก
(Erudite)
(หอปรัชญา)
Such an outrageous mistake.
เรื่องเข้าใจผิดในวันนี้
You've embarrassed the Yan family!
ทำให้สกุลเหยียนอับอายยิ่งนัก
I didn't say I was marrying Sang Qi.
ข้าไม่เคยพูดว่าข้าจะแต่งกับซางฉี
It was you who misunderstood.
ท่านเข้าใจข้าผิดไปเอง
The order will be given to us soon.
อีกไม่นานเจ้าก็จะรับตำแหน่งขุนนางแล้ว
Until then,
ช่วงนี้ให้เจ้า
stay inside the house.
อยู่แต่ในจวน
You're not going anywhere.
ไม่ให้ไปไหนเด็ดขาด
Mother!
ท่านแม่
I'll handpick a wife for you as soon as I can
ข้าจะรีบหาหญิงที่เหมาะสม
so you can get married.
มาเป็นคู่ครองให้เจ้า
Don't even try to consider
พวกดอกไม้ริมทาง
the lowly women out there.
เจ้าอย่าได้ฝันว่าจะได้แต่งด้วย
Lian Pian is not a lowly woman.
เหลียนเพียนไม่ใช่ดอกไม้ริมทาง
She is a daughter of a reputable family.
นางเป็นหญิงในจวนที่มีเกียรติ
She is just a servant.
แต่อย่างไรนางก็เป็นแค่สาวใช้
She has no place in our family.
ในบ้านสกุลเหยียนไม่มีแม้แต่ฐานะอันใด
I'm going out anyway.
ยังไงข้าก็จะออกไปอยู่ดี
Noble Consort, Young Master Zhuo requests an audience with you.
ท่านกุ้ยเฟย คุณชายจั๋วมาขอพบ
Let him in.
ให้เข้ามาได้
Aunt, you're in a good mood today.
อาหญิงวันนี้อารมณ์ดียิ่งนัก
Did something great happen?
มีเรื่องดี ๆ อะไรหรือ
I got a little closer to His Majesty.
พักนี้ข้ากับฝ่าบาทได้ใกล้ชิดกันมากขึ้น
His Majesty rewarded me tonight.
ฝ่าบาทยังพระราชทานของให้ข้าด้วย
Sit.
นั่งลงสิ
Everything is going well for the Zhuo family.
ตอนนี้สกุลจั๋วของเราฐานะมั่นคง
You must make progress with the daughter of the Sang family.
เจ้าคงต้องรีบใช้โอกาสนี้ เอาลูกสาวสกุลซางมาให้ได้
Everyone in the Imperial College knows Sang Qi and Yan Yun Zhi
ความสัมพันธ์ระหว่างซางฉี กับเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
are madly in love.
ผู้คนรู้กันไปทั่ว
Fighting for a chance at her
ถึงข้าได้นางมา
is basically pointless.
จะมีประโยชน์อะไร
Does it matter?
แล้วยังไง
Do not mind the trivial matters.
ไม่ต้องไปสนใจประเด็นเล็กน้อยพวกนี้
Without their parents' consent and a proper procedure,
ถ้าพ่อแม่ไม่อนุญาต
there are chances they might not get married.
สองคนนั้นก็แต่งงานกันไม่ได้อยู่ดี
With your wits,
เจ้าเป็นคนฉลาด
you can employ some tricks to alienate them.
ใช้วิธีทำให้เขาแตกแยกกันก็จบ
You are spending the night alone too, Miss Su.
เห็นทีคุณหนูซูคืนนี้ก็มาตัวคนเดียว
I was bored of staying at home.
อยู่แต่ในจวนก็เบื่อนิดหน่อย
I came to check out the streets.
เลยออกมาเดินเล่น
I have this sudden feeling
จู่ ๆ ข้าก็เหมือนคนเคว้งคว้าง
that you and I are in the same boat.
ไร้จุดหมายเหมือนคุณหนูซู
In the same boat?
คนเคว้งคว้าง
Is this supposed to be a joke?
คุณชายจั๋วกำลังหัวเราะเยาะข้าสินะ
Not at all, Miss Su.
ไหนเลยคุณหนูซู
I was making fun of myself.
ข้าแค่หัวเราะเยาะตัวเอง
Very well, Mr. Zhuo.
ว่าแต่ คุณชายจั๋ว
Why trouble yourself with worries on this pleasant night?
ฤกษ์งามยามดีเช่นนี้ถึงกลัดกลุ้มใจ
It's only a waste of time.
ก็เปล่าประโยชน์
(Qingfeng Restaurant) Why not go home and enjoy some wine?
กลับไปจวนเพื่อจิบสุรา
With some drinks,
ย้อมใจจะดีเสียกว่า
anyone can enjoy the night alone.
อยู่ตัวคนเดียวก็มีความสุขในค่ำคืนนี้ได้
It's pointless to drink alone.
นั่งดื่มคนเดียวก็ไม่มีอารมณ์
Our meeting is part of fate's plan for us.
การได้พบกันเหมือนเป็นบุญวาสนา
Miss Su.
คุณหนูซู
Since we're already at the Qingfeng Restaurant,
ไหน ๆ ข้างหน้านี้เป็นหอชิ่งเฟิง
why don't we go inside
เราก็เข้าไปนั่งข้างใน
and have a little chat?
พูดคุยกันนิดหน่อย
I don't mean to pry,
คุณหนูซูอย่าหาว่าข้าคิดมาก
but something still baffles me.
มีเรื่องหนึ่งที่ข้าสงสัยมาตลอด
Is it about me?
เรื่องข้าเหรอ
Enlighten me.
คุณชายจั๋วว่ามาได้
Yan Yun Zhi keeps his distance from you.
ข้าเห็นเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือเย็นชากับท่านมาตลอด
And now he announced his relationship with Sang Qi.
มาวันนี้เขายังรักกับซางฉีอย่างเปิดเผย
Why are you still obsessed with him?
ทำไมคุณหนูซูยังไม่ลืมเขา
That's because
นั่นเป็นเพราะว่าคุณชายจั๋ว
you don't know him like I do.
เห็นเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือแค่ด้านเดียว
How so?
ถ้างั้นท่านลองว่ามา
I remember
ข้าจำได้ว่า
when I was eight,
ตอนข้าอายุแปดขวบ มีอยู่ครั้งหนึ่ง
my elder brother and I were playing hide-and-seek in the garden.
พี่ข้าเล่นซ่อนหากับข้าในสวนอยู่
I was searching for him blindfolded
ข้าปิดตาพยายามหา
for quite some time.
หาอยู่ตั้งนาน
I was getting impatient and walked quickly.
ข้าเดินไวมาก
I started grabbing anything I could,
เอื้อมไปจับโน่นนี่มั่วไปหมด
and I grabbed someone.
แล้วจู่ ๆ ข้าก็จับได้คนหนึ่ง
I was so happy.
ตอนนั้นข้าดีใจมาก
What happened next?
หลังจากนั้นล่ะ
Then, I realized I grabbed his hand instead.
หลังจากนั้นข้าดึงตัวเขาอยู่
Yun Zhi held my hand, and we walked for some distance.
อวิ๋นจือจูงมือข้าเดินไปไกลมาก
He only raised his head when we reached the eaves.
จนถึงชายคาเรือนจึงเงยหน้า
He asked my brother to come down.
ไปเรียกพี่ข้าลงมา
Later on,
หลังจากนั้น
my brother made fun of him over this matter.
พี่ข้ายังล้อเขาอยู่เรื่อยว่า
He asked Yun Zhi why he didn't say anything,
ทำไมไม่บอกว่าจับผิดคน
and whether he was trying to take advantage of me.
คิดจะเอาเปรียบผู้หญิงอย่างข้าใช่ไหม
Yun Zhi answered with a stiff expression.
ตอนนั้นอวิ๋นจือตอบ
Back then,
แบบหน้าตายว่า
I walked into a flower bed
เป็นเพราะสวนที่ข้าเดินผ่าน
with Chinese Roses.
เป็นสวนดอกกุหลาบ
The plants were full of thorns.
ก้านกุหลาบมีหนาม
If I fell into the bushes,
กลัวว่าถ้าข้าหกล้ม
I'd be badly hurt.
จะต้องบาดเจ็บเป็นแน่
Yan Yun Zhi did what anyone should.
เรื่องนี้ต่อให้เป็นคนอื่น ก็ต้องทำแบบเดียวกัน
If I were the one who held your hand,
ถ้าตอนนั้นคนที่จูงท่านเป็นข้าแทน
would you fall in love with me instead?
ท่านก็คงอยากแต่งงานกับข้าใช่ไหม
Miss Su.
คุณหนูซู
You knew all along
ท่านรู้แต่แรกแล้วว่า
that Yan Yun Zhi
เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือไม่ได้
doesn't love you.
มีใจให้ท่าน
At this point,
ในเมื่อท่านพูดออกมาถึงขั้นนี้
I should take my leave.
ข้าคงไม่อาจอยู่ต่อแล้ว
See you.
ข้าขออำลา
Miss Su, wait.
ช้าก่อนคุณหนูซู
I know you are a gentle person.
ข้ารู้ว่าคุณหนูซูภายนอกเป็นคนอ่อนโยน
But you wouldn't give up easily.
แต่ข้างในเป็นคนมุ่งมั่นตั้งใจ
Do you believe in destiny
คุณหนูเลือกจะเชื่อในพรหมลิขิต
or will you decide the future yourself?
หรือเชื่อว่าตัวเองเปลี่ยนแปลงชะตาฟ้าได้
As you said,
คุณชายจั๋วพูดเองว่า
Yan Yun Zhi doesn't love me.
เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือไม่มีใจให้ข้า
I have no place in his heart.
ใจเขาไม่อยู่ที่ข้า
Should I force him into loving me?
แล้วจะให้ข้าบีบบังคับเขาหรือ
If you can't have his heart,
ถ้าท่านยังมัดใจเขาไม่ได้
you can first get close to him.
ท่านก็มัดตัวเขาให้ได้ก่อน
When a bond is formed between two people,
หากคนสองคนถูกผูกมัดไว้ด้วยกัน
as they eat at the same table
กินข้าวร่วมโต๊ะกัน
and share the same bed,
นอนเตียงเดียวกัน
it's only a matter of time
นานวันเข้า
before you can win his love.
ท่านก็จะได้ใจเขาไปเอง
Miss Su, I want to have Sang Qi for myself.
คุณหนูซู ข้าเองอยากได้ซางฉี
But do you
แต่ก็ขึ้นอยู่กับว่า
want to have Yan Yun Zhi's love?
ท่านอยากได้เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือหรือไม่
(Qiqiao Festival) Great!
(เทศกาลชีซี) เยี่ยม
Miss, the shop is closed.
คุณหนู ร้านเราปิดแล้ว
We cannot serve you.
คุณหนูเชิญไปร้านอื่นเถอะ
It's your honor to have me
ข้ามาดื่มเหล้าที่ร้านเจ้า
(Wang's Dumplings) as your customer.
ถือเป็นเกียรติของเจ้าด้วยซ้ำ
Who do you think you are?
เจ้าคิดว่าตัวเองเป็นใคร
How dare you chase me away?
กล้าไล่ข้าไปเหรอ
I'll get the Grand Tutor's men
จะให้ข้าเอาคนจากจวนไท่ฟู่
to trash your shop.
มาพังร้านเจ้าเหรอ
Don't be so full of yourself.
คำพูดเจ้าไม่เบา
You?
ระดับเจ้า
The daughter of the Grand Tutor
ลูกสาวจวนไท่ฟู่
is drinking all by herself on this festive night?
มาดื่มเหล้าคนเดียวคืนนี้
You...
เจ้า
Just you wait.
เจ้าจำไว้
Stand aside.
หลบไป
Leave.
- ไปเถอะ ไปเถอะ - ไป ไป ไป
No one dares to bullies a woman when I'm around.
ต่อหน้าข้าไม่มีใครกล้าผลักไสสตรี
Now go away.
ยังไม่รีบไปอีก
Let's go.
ไป ไป ไป
So it's you.
เป็นเจ้าเองเหรอ
You could at least thank me.
ขอบคุณสักคำก็ไม่มีนะ
It's what a man should have done.
นี่เป็นเรื่องที่บุรุษควรทำอยู่แล้ว
Miss Song.
คุณหนูซ่ง
You look gorgeous in the dress.
วันนี้แต่งตัวมาซะสะสวย
I bet you went to the Magpie Bridge tonight. [*Usually with one's lover]
คงไปพบหวานใจมาสินะ
I'm not as debauched as you, Zhuo Wen Yuan.
ข้าไม่ได้เจ้าชู้เหมือนเจ้าสักหน่อย
Only Yan Yun Zhi
ถ้าข้าจะนัดพบใคร
can walk the Magpie Bridge with me.
คนคนนั้นต้องเป็นเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
I can be certain
ถ้าเป็นแบบนั้น
that you'll be alone tonight.
เห็นทีคืนนี้เจ้าคงอยู่ตัวคนเดียว
You...
นี่เจ้า
Speak about yourself.
เจ้าก็พอกันแหละ
You should try winning Sang Qi back
ยังจะมาหัวเราะเยาะข้า
instead of mocking me.
ไปจีบซางฉีให้ได้ก่อนเถอะ
I'm lonely?
กล้ามาว่าข้าว่าตัวคนเดียว
What about you? You failed to win her heart
ข้าไม่เหมือนเจ้าหรอก ตามตื๊อเขาสารพัด
with the displays of affection.
สุดท้ายก็คว้าน้ำเหลว
You even embarrassed yourself.
แถมหน้าแตกด้วย
Miss Song, getting upset at me won't do you any good.
คุณหนูซ่ง เจ้าระบายอารมณ์ใส่ข้า ไม่มีประโยชน์
I won't fall for it.
ข้าไม่หลงกลเจ้าหรอกนะ
I won't waste any time cheering you up.
ข้าไม่มีแม้แต่เวลาจะง้อเจ้า
Cheering me up?
เจ้าจะง้อข้าเหรอ
I wouldn't need you
ใครให้เจ้าง้อ
even if all men went extinct.
ผู้ชายทั้งโลกตายไปหมดแล้วเหรอ
Jing Mu.
จิ่งมู่
Yes.
ขอรับ
Please escort Miss Song back to her home.
ช่วยพาคุณหนูซ่งกลับจวนด้วย
It's too dangerous for her to be out here alone at night.
ดึกดื่นค่ำคืนแล้วยังมาตัวคนเดียว
Yes.
ขอรับ
Zhuo Wen Yuan!
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
Go back to your master.
เจ้าไปกับนายเจ้า
I don't need his help!
ข้าไม่ต้องการความหวังดี
Hold still.
กุมตัวไว้ให้ดี
Stay still.
บอกมาตามตรง
Qi Lang.
ชีหลาง
San Lang. What is it?
ซานหลาง เกิดเรื่องอะไรขึ้น
After you were ambushed at the border of Jingzhou
หลังจากเหตุการณ์ที่เจ้า ถูกซุ่มโจมตีที่จิงโจว
and the assassination towards Official Wei,
และใต้เท้าเว่ยโดนสังหาร
I've been investigating
ข้าก็แอบสืบเบาะแสที่สกุลเว่ย
for leads the Wei family might have left.
อาจหลงเหลือไว้มาตลอด
Have you learned who the mastermind is?
เจ้าเจอหรือยังว่าเป็นฝีมือใคร
Not yet.
ยัง
When we arrived at the Wei Residence,
ตอนที่เราไปถึงบ้านสกุลเว่ย
someone got ahead of us and went through the house.
พบว่ามีคนไปทำลายหลักฐาน ก่อนหน้าเราแล้ว
But there were witnesses in the neighborhood.
ดีที่ว่าพักนี้มีคนพบเห็นว่า
Recently,
มีคนเข้า ๆ ออก ๆ
a man who sells the Wei family's furniture off
บ้านสกุลเว่ย เอาของใช้ที่ได้จากบ้าน
has been to the house.
มาขายต่อ
He may seem like a merchant
คนคนนี้
who sells the furniture off,
คือพ่อค้าที่ขายของบ้านสกุลเว่ย
but he's actually a spy from Xizhao.
เบื้องต้นพบว่าเป็นสายลับของซีเจา
If he has the order to search this place
ในเมื่อคนคนนี้ได้รับคำสั่งมา
and is in contact with his comrades,
แปลว่ายังติดต่อกับผู้สั่งการอยู่
he's likely to know who the mastermind is.
น่าจะช่วยให้เราสืบสาวตัวผู้บงการได้
Now
แบบนี้
there is hope to find out which official is commanding
มีหวังได้เจอตัวคนในราชสำนักที่สมคบกับ
and contacting Xizhao.
ทางซีเจา
Yes.
ถูกต้อง
This is their hideout.
ที่ตรงนี้เป็นฐานที่มั่นของพวกมัน
Since Yu was involved,
ข้าว่าเรื่องนี้ มีส่วนเกี่ยวข้องกับพี่อวี่
you'd want to join the investigation.
เจ้าคงอยากสืบไปพร้อม ๆ กัน
That's why I notified you.
ข้าถึงได้รีบให้เจ้ามาช่วยในวันนี้
Come.
มา
Qi Lang, some of the goods here
ชีหลาง ดูเหมือนว่าของพวกนี้
have been transported away.
มีคนขนออกไปแล้วบางส่วน
Let's go inside.
ไปดูทางนั้นกัน
Yes.
ได้
No sudden movement!
อยู่นิ่ง ๆ
Unveil it.
เปิด
This should be the plant Xizhao uses.
พืชชนิดนี้น่าจะเป็นพืชจากซีเจา
It has never been seen in Bianjing.
ไม่เคยเห็นในเมืองเปี้ยนจิงมาก่อน
The powder that poisoned Sang Qi
ยาพิษที่ซางฉีโดน
must have been extracted from this plant.
น่าจะสกัดมาจากพืชชนิดนี้
Tell us,
บอกมา
who ordered you to transport the plants here?
ใครเป็นคนสั่งให้เจ้าขนของพวกนี้มาที่นี่
I didn't bring the plants here.
ข้า ข้าไม่ได้เป็นคนขนมา
I was hired to guard the smuggled salt.
ข้าแค่เฝ้าดูแลเกลือที่ลักลอบขนมา
Then I'll transport the salt
แล้วค่อยเอาเกลือส่งไปจุดอื่นตามคำสั่ง
to other places based on the orders.
ส่งไปที่จุดอื่น
Probably someone was given the order to bring the plants here.
ของพวกนี้น่าจะเป็นคนอื่นขนมาตามคำสั่ง
San Lang, come with me.
ซานหลาง เจ้าตามข้ามา
I suspect
ข้าคิดว่า
someone in Bianjing sells the smuggled salt
เปี้ยนจิงน่าจะเป็นจุดขนถ่าย เกลือเถื่อน
to Xizhao.
ไปถึงมือของซีเจา
They traded it
ส่วนซีเจาเอง
to have Xizhao's poisonous plants transported here.
ก็ส่งไม้มีพิษพวกนี้กลับมาเปี้ยนจิง เป็นการแลกเปลี่ยน
Both the mastermind and Xizhao profit.
ทั้งสองฝ่ายต่างได้ผลประโยชน์
This place
และจุดนี้
should be one of the hideouts they use
น่าจะเป็นจุดที่ช่วยสร้างรายได้
for their illicit business.
เป็นกอบเป็นกำ
They all have the pass.
อีกอย่างคนพวกนี้มีใบผ่านแดนทุกคน
They can travel freely.
ทำให้เดินทางสะดวก
Whoever is working in the dark
เห็นที คนที่คอยวางแผนเส้นทาง
put great effort into securing
คิดแผนมาอย่างรัดกุม
this transportation route.
เพื่อเปิดเส้นทางขนส่งเส้นนี้
The Wei family is incapable of pulling this off.
ลำพังสกุลเว่ยไม่น่าจะลงมือเองได้
Don't you find the scent odd?
เจ้าได้กลิ่นอะไรแปลกประหลาดไหม
Now that you said it,
เจ้าพูดแบบนี้ข้าก็เพิ่งนึกออก
it smells pretty pleasant.
ข้างนี้มีกลิ่นหอมพอควร
Pleasant?
กลิ่นหอม
Yes.
ใช่
It's about the same fragrance
กลิ่นเหมือนแป้งหอมที่สตรี
used by the ladies.
ทั่วไปใช้กัน
There is no way this is fragrance.
นี่หาใช่แป้งหอมที่สตรีใช้กัน
My nose hurt when I entered.
ข้าเข้ามาปุ๊บก็รู้สึกกลิ่นฉุน
Qi Lang.
ชีหลาง
You don't look so good.
ดูเจ้าไม่ค่อยปกติ
Your nose is swelling.
จมูกเจ้าเช็ดจนแดงไปหมดแล้ว
You should go home and rest.
เจ้ารีบกลับไปพักผ่อนก่อนเถอะ
Well...
แล้วที่นี่
Leave the rest to me.
ข้าจะดูแลเรื่องนี้เอง
It's the Prefecture Court's duty after all.
นี่เป็นเรื่องที่จวนจิงจ้าวดูแลอยู่แล้ว
My men will seal off this warehouse
ข้าจะสั่งให้คนปิดบ้านหลังนี้
and secure evidence.
และรีบค้นหาหลักฐาน
I'm counting on you.
รบกวนเจ้าด้วย
It's part of my job.
เป็นหน้าที่ข้าอยู่แล้ว
(Qingfeng Restaurant, Shuiyue Shop)
(หอชิ่งเฟิง)
Yan Yun Zhi and Yan San Lang
ครั้งนี้เราถูกเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
caught us off guard this time.
กับเหยียนซานหลางเล่นงาน
The warehouse has been raided.
บ้านที่อยู่นอกเมืองก็ถูกยึด
The goods are now confiscated.
สินค้าก็ถูกยึด
But fortunately,
ยังดีที่ว่า
they didn't find the ledger.
พวกเขายังไม่ได้เจอสมุดบัญชี
Be more cautious with the operation.
ช่วงนี้จะทำอะไรต้องเพิ่มความระมัดระวัง
Yan San Lang has eyes and ears everywhere.
เหยียนซานหลางน่าจะวางกำลังไว้ทั่วแล้ว
Remember,
จำไว้
do not operate near that warehouse.
ห้ามเข้าไปใกล้บ้านหลังนั้นเด็ดขาด
Yes.
รับทราบ
And reduce the number of deliveries.
อีกอย่าง ลดความถี่ในการขนส่งสินค้าด้วย
They are waiting for us to make a mistake.
พวกเขากำลังรอทีเผลอ
Madam Zhang.
ป้าจาง
Please proceed as Young Master Zhuo ordered.
ท่านช่วยสั่งการลงไป ตามคำสั่งของคุณชายจั๋ว
Yes.
รับทราบ
Young Master.
คุณชาย
What news do you bear?
มีข่าวอะไรว่ามา
Yan Yun Zhi proposed,
เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือไปจวนไท่เว่ยสู่ขอคุณหนูซาง
but Grand Commandant Sang didn't give his consent.
แต่ซางไท่เว่ยปฏิเสธไป
Madam, Miss Su is here.
ฮูหยิน แม่นางซูมาแล้ว
Come in.
ให้เข้ามาเร็วเข้า
Madam.
ท่านป้า
You are here, Lan.
หลานจีมาแล้วเหรอ
You came at bad timing.
วันนี้มาเสียเที่ยวแล้ว
The orders for the imperial examination came in today.
วันนี้มีพิธีแต่งตั้งคนที่สอบราชการผ่าน
Yun Zhi is currently away.
อวิ๋นจือไม่อยู่ที่จวน
(If you can't have his heart,)
(ถ้าท่านยังมัดใจเขาไม่ได้)
you can first get close to him.
(ท่านก็มัดตัวเขาให้ได้ก่อน)
When a bond is formed between two people,
(หากคนสองคนถูกผูกมัดไว้ด้วยกัน)
as they eat at the same table
(กินข้าวร่วมโต๊ะกัน)
and share the same bed,
(นอนเตียงเดียวกัน)
it's only a matter of time
(นานวันเข้า)
before you can win his love.
(ท่านก็จะได้ใจเขาไปเอง)
I came to have a chat with you.
ข้าแค่มาชวนท่านป้าพูดคุยเล่น
I know you'll be alone in the house,
ข้ารู้ว่าท่านอยู่แต่ในจวนทุกวัน
so I prepared some snacks for you.
ข้าเลยทำขนมมาให้ท่านชิมดู
I appreciate it.
เยี่ยมเลยนะ
It's been so long since you last came here.
หลานจีไม่ได้มาที่นี่นานเหมือนกันนะ
Please, have a seat.
มา เร็วเข้า มานั่งเร็ว
I know I shouldn't visit
ข้ารู้ตัวว่า ฐานะอย่างข้า
because of my past with him.
มาที่จวนท่านคงไม่ค่อยเหมาะสม
After all, Yun Zhi
อีกอย่างเห็นว่า
went to the Grand Commandant's Residence to propose.
อวิ๋นจือเองก็ไปสู่ขอคนที่จวนไท่เว่ยแล้ว
What was that?
เจ้าว่าอะไรนะ
Who went to the Grand Commandant's Residence to propose?
ใครไปสู่ขอคนที่จวนไท่เว่ย
♪As our fate intertwined, which life should we pick?♪
♪รอโชคชะตาที่เริ่มครอบงำชีวิต♪
♪I'm willing to this life for a chance to meet you in every life♪
♪ยินยอมแลกทั้งชีวิตให้แก่กันและกัน♪
♪Many woes and sorrows fill my existence♪
♪มีความคิดนับพันติดค้างในใจข้า♪
♪If persevering♪
♪หากความรักที่มั่นคง♪
♪Makes us fall in love with each other♪
♪กลายเป็นความรักลึกซึ้งของกันและกัน♪
♪That's how I come to this life♪
♪ข้าถึงได้มีชั่วชีวิตนี้♪
♪If not letting go of my past♪
♪หากการเริ่มหวนคิดเรื่องเก่า♪
♪Becomes my mistake♪
♪กลายเป็นความผิดพลั้งของข้า♪
♪This beautiful story♪
♪หากเรื่องราวที่สมบูรณ์ดั่งสัญญา♪
♪Is like the way I look when I make up my mind♪
♪บังเอิญพบกับตัวข้าที่แน่วแน่♪
♪But my heart changed its mind♪
♪ดวงใจกลับแปรเปลี่ยนจุดเริ่มต้น♪
♪At the dawn♪
♪ในห้วงเวลาที่น้ำค้างหยด♪
♪What an unexpected love♪
♪ไม่รู้ว่าชะตาความรักเป็นอย่างไร♪
♪And so I wrote my words with joy♪
♪ข้าเขียนบทกวีแห่งความสุข♪
♪I have accepted this life I reincarnated in♪
♪ข้าก็จะยอมรับช่วงชีวิตที่หมุนเวียน♪
♪May this budding romance♪
♪นำความรักจากความเฉยชา♪
♪Develop into something unforgettable♪
♪หล่อหลอมจนเป็นลวดลายที่ชัดเจน♪